

Ovande Furtado Jr Associate Professor

March 2024

(

Department of Kinesiology, California State University-Northridge



+1 818 677 5968



drfurtado.us



ovandef@csun.edu



ofurtado



drfurtado

About me -

Dr. Furtado received a B.A. in Physical Education from the Federal University of Parana, Curitiba, PR - Brazil. He earned his M.S. and Ph.D. degrees in Motor Behavior from the University of Pittsburgh, PA. Dr. Furtado's line of research focuses on two main areas: (1) validation of observational models in psychomotor assessment instruments and (2) the relationship between motor skill competence, perceived motor competence, physical activity levels, and body composition.

Education

1997

2009	Ph.D. Motor Behavior Pittsburgh, PA	Universityh of Pittsburgh
2004	M.S. Motor Behavior Pittsburgh, PA	Universityh of Pittsburgh

Professional Appointments

B.A Kinesiology

Curitiba, Brazil

· 2013-Present: Associate Professor, California State University-Northridge

Federal Univertsity of Paraná

- 2007-2013: Associate Professor, Eastern Illinois University
- 2006-2007: K-8 Physical Education Teacher, Falk School
- 2001-2005: Program Co-Director, Kinder Kinetics Movement Program

Frequently Taught Courses (CSUN)

- KIN 377 Motor Learning and Control
- KIN 477 Motor Development
- KIN 610 Quantitative Analysis of Research in Kinesiology

Selected Publications

Azurdia, D., Acuña, S. M., Narasaki-Jara, M., Furtado Jr, O., & Jung, T. (2022). Effects of virtual reality-based aerobic exercise on perceptions of pain and fatigue in individuals with spinal cord injury. Games for Health Journal, 11(4), 236–241. https://doi.org/10.1089/g4h.2021.0151

Ladewig, I., Boell, I. B., Pereira, B. O., Spinelli, A. H., Franz, L. G., & Furtado Jr, O. (2019). The efficacy of using learning cues to teach children perform the backhand. Journal of Physical Education and Sports Management, 6(1). https://doi.org/10.15640/jpesm.v6nla6

Mazzardo, O., Fontana, F. E., Furtado Jr, O., & Gallagher, J. D. (2018). The relationship of movement skills with habitual and organized physical activity in seven and eight-year-old children. Pensar a Prática, 21(1), 135–146. https://doi.org/10.5216/rpp.v21i1.42360

Beals, T., Furtado Jr, O., & Fontana, F. E. (2018). Relative age effect and academic timing in american junior college baseball. Perceptual and Motor Skills, 125(1), 147–161. https://doi.org/10.1177/0031512517724260

Furtado Jr, O., & Gallagher, J. D. (2018). Expert-rater agreement and inter-/intrarater reliability for the Furtado-Gallagher Computerized Observational Movement Pattern Assessment System. Perceptual and Motor Skills, 125(3), 423-437. https://doi.org/10.1177/0031512518769205

Fontana, F. E., Furtado Jr, O., Mazzardo, O., Hong, D., & Campos, W. de. (2017). Anti-fat bias by professors teaching physical education majors. European Physical Education Review, 23(1), 127–138. https://doi.org/10.1177/1356336X16643304

Fontana, F. E., Furtado Jr, O., Marston, R., Mazzardo, O., & Gallagher, J. D. (2013). Anti-fat bias among physical education teachers and majors. The Physical Educator, 70(1), 15–31.

Furtado Jr, O., & Gallagher, J. D. (2012). The reliability of classification decisions for the Furtado-Gallagher Computerized Observational Movement Pattern Assessment System—FG-COMPASS. Research Quarterly for Exercise and Sport, 83(3), 383–390. https://doi.org/10.1080/02701367.2012.10599872

Fontana, F. E., Mazzardo, O., Furtado Jr, O., & Gallagher, J. D. (2009). Whole and part practice: A meta-analysis. Perceptual and Motor Skills, 109(2), 517-530. https://doi.org/10.2466/pms.109.2.517-530

Fontana, F. E., Mazzardo, O., Mokgothu, C., Furtado Jr, O., & Gallagher, J. D. (2009). Influence of exercise intensity on the decision-making performance of experienced and inexperienced soccer players. Journal of Sport & Exercise Psychology, 31(2), 135–151.